בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ז. Chaf-Zayin. We pick
up with the משנה Mishnah on כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf-Vav Amud-Beis. So
we are now going through the, we went through the normal way
in a normal day that the various lotteries, lot drawings, that would
happen in order to distribute the עבודות avodot related to the first
thing in the morning, to the תמיד, tamid, and then the burning
of the קטורת, ketoret, and then the final part of bringing the
limbs of the animal up to the altar.
We don't really know, there was a discussion in the גמרא Gemara
about how they would distribute the afternoon תמיד, tamid, whether that was
based on the same lottery or was that different people based on
the same lottery or was that the same people.
And we did not discuss yet anything about the other קרבנות korbanot
during the day. So we pick up now. There is one final
point that I did want to mention. I think we ran out
of time the other time. The משנה Mishnah had said, the previous
משנה Mishnah spoke about how the תמיד tamid was brought with nine
people, meaning that they were divided between those that would bring up
the pieces of meat, the pieces of the animal, and those that
would bring up the wine and the flour and the other things
that accompanied it, but it said it could get up to 12
based on if it was the afternoon, if it was סוכות, Sukkot,
and so on. The very last statement, let's reread the last statement
right before the משנה. Mishnah. So again, the משנה Mishnah said nine
to 12 in terms of how many people bringing up the various
limbs of the תמיד, tamid, with which associated, with the attendant types
of things that were burnt on the altar. And the last ברייתא
Baraita says, תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiya, it's two lines, three
lines before the משנה, Mishnah, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught in a
ברייתא, Baraita, פיס פעמים י"ג. Payis pe'amim yod-gimmel.
Sometimes there would be 13 people, because if you remember, the previous
משנה Mishnah said the תמיד tamid was 13 because there were four
עבודות avodot that preceded the bringing of the limbs: the שחיטה, shechting,
the throwing of the blood, the cleaning of the gold altar, and
the cleaning of the מנורה. menorah. So therefore those four preceded the
bringing of the limbs. So the nine to 12 of our משנה
Mishnah is going to become nine to 16. So פעמים י"ג פעמים
י"ד פעמים ט"ו פעמים ט"ז. pe'amim yod-gimmel, pe'amim yod-dalet, pe'amim tet-vav, pe'amim
tet-zayin. It could be 16. Four for the things that preceded, and
then 12 in the most extreme cases with the logs of wood,
or with the water, and so on, 12 for the bringing of
the תמיד tamid and the other things that were brought to the
altar with it. Now the reason I wanted to just repeat this
was to point out the last thing. ותניא י"ז, Ve-tanya yod-zayin, one
ברייתא Baraita says it got up to 17. ההיא דלא
כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב אלא כרבי יהודה. Hahi d'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov ela k'Rabbi Yehuda. Now that's not like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, why? Because as you might remember, רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, says that,
one minute, right, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says
that you would not have another person bring up the limbs to
the altar,
rather it's going like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who as the גמרא
Gemara said before, presumably argues on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov and says that there would be other people who would
bring up the limbs from the altar. Now the only reason I
wanted to point this up is, how does that get you one
more? Right? The position that argues on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov again
says that the same people who brought it to the כבש kevesh
would bring it from the כבש kevesh to the top of the
altar, so there would be no extra people. Then there is an
opinion that disagreed and said no, no, no, there was a fourth
lottery and other people would bring it from the ramp to the
top of the altar. But according to this, you only went up
from 16 to 17. So רש"י Rashi says, and תוספות Tosafot has
a different read of the גמרא, Gemara, but רש"י Rashi says based
on this that the bringing up from the ramp to the top
of the altar was not done by nine new people, it was
done by one person. So like nine people brought the stuff to
the כבש kevesh and then one person came and brought it all
from the כבש kevesh to the top of the altar. And just
if you look at רש"י Rashi just four lines before the line
that got why, אלא כרבי יהודה, ela k'Rabbi Yehuda, he says והוא
תנא אית ליה עוד כהן אחד המעלה אברים מן הכבש למזבח דהרי
כאן י"ז. v'hu tanna is lei od kohen echad hama'aleh evarim min
hakevesh lamizbe'ach harei kan yod-zayin. So I just wanted to point that
out because I thought that was quite startling. You have so many
people bringing the limbs, bringing the stuff to the altar, from nine
to 12 people bringing the limbs and all this stuff to the
altar, and then when we say it gets finished from the כבש,
kevesh, I mean to the כבש, kevesh, and then to get finished
from the כבש kevesh to the top, according to רש"י, Rashi, it
was one guy who just went back and forth and back and
forth. So it's a little bit bizarre. Okay, now let's look at
the next משנה Mishnah that
speaks about— What about lighting the candles in the evening?
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot sort of discusses that, whether it was the
same guy who lit them in the morning lit them in the
evening. The גמרא Gemara does not discuss that.
But I thought we did not necessarily light them in the morning,
right?
I mean, clean them in the morning, lit them in the evening.
Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה. Mishnah. So
that is in terms of the תמיד, tamid, which is a lamb.
איל קרב באחד עשר, Ayil karev b'achad-asar, you would have 11 כהנים
kohanim bringing a ram, right? הבשר בחמשה, Habasar b'chamisha, five with the
for the meat, the various members of the animal, you know, the
various sections of the animal you would have five. Okay, let's take
a look now at the next משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. So that's in
terms of the תמיד tamid, *Tamid*, which is a lamb. איל ayil
*Ayil*, if you have a ram, קרב באחד עשר *karev beachad asar*,
you would have eleven כהנים kohanim *kohanim* bringing a ram, right? הבשר
בחמישה *Habasar bechamishah*, five with the for the meat, the various meat,
the various sections of the animal, you'd have five כהנים kohanim *kohanim*.
הקרביים והסולת והיין בשניים שניים *Hakirvayim vehasolet vehayayin bishnayim bishnayim*. Now here's
the way it would be so much more than the lamb, because
the innards, the flour, and the wine, those would be divided, each
there would be two כהנים kohanim *kohanim* for each one of those,
two כהנים kohanim *kohanim* bringing the various inner organs, you'd divide it
between two, two כהנים kohanim *kohanim* bringing the flour that came with
the מנחת נסכים nesachim. *minchat nesachim*, the מנחה *mincha* that accompanied the
קרבן korban. *korban*, and two כהנים kohanim. *kohanim* bringing the wine. Now
again, it's a little wild. I mean, one כהן kohen. *kohen* is
to bring a huge limb, but for a little bit extra wine,
cause a ram has a little more wine than a lamb, okay,
and a ram has a little bit more flour than a lamb,
so one oh we have a little more flour, divide it between
two כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*. One guy has to carry the whole hindquarters
of this animal. So apparently again some of this is symbolic, the
same way we said before that two כהנים kohanim *kohanim* would be
carrying the two little cups of the incense, right, for the, you
know, for the שולחן *shulchan*. So sometimes it was just completely symbolic
to signify what was being done. So because there was a little
extra flour, a little extra wine, in order to signify that it
was more than the lamb, that there was an increase in the
flour and the wine, we have two כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* for each
one of those rather than one כהן kohen.
*kohen*. Each of them took like whatever it is, with two?
Presumably half. Yeah.
So one took like one low container, the other took like another
low container.
Presumably. No, no, no, they would divide it up. Okay, so that's
how you get there eleven as opposed to nine. פר קרב בעשרים
וארבע *Par karev be'esrim ve'arba*. Now a cow, which really needs a
lot more כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim* to carry it, would be twenty-four people,
not nine and not eleven. How do you get there? הראש והרגל
*Harosh veha'regel*.
So first let's start with the head and the and the and
the hind leg, the right hind leg. So if you remember before
that was all carried by one כהן kohen. *kohen* by a lamb,
but here, הראש באחד *harosh be'echad*, one to carry the head, הרגל
בשניים *haregel bishnayim*, two כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* just to carry the leg,
and this here Michael they probably would be carrying it together, okay,
cause they carry the whole hind leg. Okay. העוקץ והרגל
*Ha'ukatz veha'regel*, now how about the tail and the other hindquarters? Again,
by a lamb that was one כהן Kohen. *kohen*. Here העוקץ בשניים
*ha'ukatz bishnayim*, right, the rump, so the rump, you know, whatever, would
be with two and the tail, and not just the tail, there's
two, והרגל בשניים *veha'regel bishnayim*, and again the other hindquarters another two.
החזה והגרה *Hechazeh vehagerah*, the chest and the throat, so again in
a lamb it would be one. Here, החזה באחד והגרה בשלושה *hechazeh
be'echad vehagerah bishloshah*. So the chest was one and the whole throat
area,
again I don't know cause it contained, I'm not exactly sure how
they divided it up, but I assume it would have contained this
part as well, the chest might have been like the side part.
With three?
That takes three people?
I don't know. שתי ידיים *Shtei yadayim*, now the two forearms, בשניים
*bishnayim*, two כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*, presumably one per כהן Kohen. *kohen*. ושתי
דפנות *Ve'shtei defanot*, the two flanks, בשניים *bishnayim*, two כהנים kohanim, *kohanim*.
הקרביים והסולת והיין *Hakirvayim
vehasolet vehayayin*, the inner, the innards, and the flour and the wine,
so the same way before that went up two per, now it's
בשלושה שלושה *bishloshah shloshah*, three per. So you can do the math,
it comes out to twenty-four. במה דברים אמורים *Bameh devarim amurim*, when
is this true that we would divide it up this way between
nine or eleven or twenty-four,
so I mean between nine or twelve or twenty-four, בקרבנות ציבור tzibur
*bekorbenot tzibbur*, in the communal sacrifices. Cause there you wanted there to
be like a lot of כהנים kohanim *kohanim* involved and it to
be shown like it's being done for all of כלל ישראל *Klal
Yisrael*, you want the involvement of many many כהנים kohanim *kohanim* to
represent that it's sort of coming for the ציבור *tzibbur* and it's
being so much... however, אבל בקרבן יחיד *aval bekorban yachid*, if an
individual brings the קרבן korban, *korban*, אם רצה להקריב מקריב *im ratzah
lehakriv makriv*, any כהן Kohen, *kohen* who wants to offer can offer
it up like there's no way of any of any particular division.
Interesting question like can the owner sort of say I'd prefer for
a particular כהן Kohen *kohen* to do it? That might be tied
into the discussion I know you had it before I think it
was when I was out about whether the כהנים kohanim *kohanim* are
our representatives or God's representatives. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* raises the issue whether
the owner can request a particular כהן Kohen. *kohen* to bring it
for him. Right here it doesn't say who is the רצה להקריב
*ratzah lehakriv*. Oh I want to do it or I want to
do it, you know I mean so what if there's a fight
about it? But anyway there would not be any clear system of
dividing it, you know, it would be done on an ad hoc
basis. הפשטן וניתוחן של אלו ואלו *Hafshatan venittuchan shel elu ve'elu*, but
whether the קרבן ציבור korban tzibur. *korban tzibbur* or the קרבן korban
יחיד *korban yachid*, the flaying and the dismembering, שווים *shavin*, would be
done the same. Now what does that mean would be done the
same? It could just mean that again there wasn't any particular system,
it would be ad hoc. The only system would be for these
קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur. *korbanot tzibbur* getting as many כהנים kohanim *kohanim*
involved as possible. Now I emphasized this point about what we're saying
as the line of division is whether many כהנים kohanim. *kohanim* do
it and we divide it up or whether you know whether there's
whoever's in charge of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash* says
okay here's going to be the division dot dot dot or whether
it's sort of an ad hoc basis and can be even fewer,
you know, even one כהן Kohen. *kohen*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* adds another
thing which maybe should have you know you would have you would
assume but I want to point it out but two lines from
the bottom במה דברים אמורים *bameh devarim amurim* רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
דבעינן כהני כהני לכל בהמה ובעינן פייס payis *debe'inan kohani kohani lechol
behemah ube'inan payis* and we'd So you need a lottery. So the
reason I draw that out is we have yet to say that
there would ever be a פייס payis for the קרבנות ציבור. korbanot
tzibur, We've only mentioned a פייס payis. for the תמיד, Tamid right?
So there's קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibur? there's מוסף, musaf, right? So what
about other קרבנות ציבור? korbanot tzibur So
it is true though in סוכה Sukkah you see the whole discussion
about the division of the קרבנות korbanot of סוכה Sukkah being done
with a פייס payis. and all the various cows that were divided
and all the whole ways that that was divided with a פייס.
payis Okay, but it is worth noting that we have not said
anywhere that that was here at least. Yet, there's other places. סוכה
Sukkah discusses those קרבנות korbanot of the מוסף musaf but here we
have not discussed that that was done with a פייס. payis. רש"י
here pointed out actually we did sort of allude to it not
in this discussion before because if you remember the way שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeret we had a discussion of how שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret
is different than סוכות Sukkot and we said שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret
is פזר כח"ש. pezer kachash. It has distinct and what's פזר? pezer?
פייס בפני עצמו, payis bifnei atzmo, a separate פייס payis for the
קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur, for שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret as opposed to
the one that was done for the מוסף musaf for סוכות. Sukkot.
So it is worth noting although not explicit in these משניות mishnayot
that not only would it have many כהנים kohanim and divide up
the various tasks in a particular way but it would have a
special פייס. payis And again I think the significance of this is
for the קרבנות korbanot. ציבור, you could say it's an honor, you
could say whatever, but again I think the significance is is that
it more sort of shows like the corporate entity of the כהנים
kohanim are involved in the bringing up of it. Not just an
individual כהן. kohen It's being orchestrated from through the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash through the offices of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and it's
being done by all the כהנים kohanim. participating. I mean if everybody
gathers together for the פייס payis in a way everybody's involved in
the process even if only a small number actually bring it. So
I think there's a ציבור element here in terms of the community
of the כהנים kohanim that is being parallel to the fact that
it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur, You had a question Norm? No.
He says on the פר של החג Par shel HaChag on סוכות
Sukkot it was twenty four כהנים kohanim per ox times seventy.
Well yes except there were also remember that on the רגלים regalim
there were also all the משמרות mishmarot were there. So the actual
division that they did there was a—the פייס payis there is a
slightly different in that it's determining which משמר mishmar does—so we give
the cow, the first cow to this משמר, mishmar, the next cow
to that משמר, mishmar, the next cow to that משמר. mishmar. Then
within the משמר mishmar presumably they divided it with twenty four כהנים.
kohanim Large number of כהנים, kohanim, it's seventy times twenty four just
for that.
Exactly. Exactly. And was there a פייס payis for—like was there a
פייס payis for the—for—so that's—it's thank you
for bringing that up though because it's important to note that the
פייס payis by the רגלים regalim was more about which משמר mishmar
would do the different things, not the division within the משמר mishmar
of the different parts of the קרבן. korban, Was there a פייס
payis on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh for the—for—was there a פייס payis,
on שבת Shabbat for the מוסף musaf of שבת? Shabbat? Right, that
is not being said here. רש"י says it. Okay. Yes. Talk about
the enormous number of נסכים. nesachim Right. Like do they actually have
if you were going to divide these נסכים just one of them
was the יין yayin and that was divided by two כהנים kohanim.
and if an איל was like a third of a הין hin
then you'd have to have a sixth of a הין hin per
כהן. kohen, You have to have that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so
they had like a only like a certain sizes, didn't they? I
don't think so. They they might have had certain sizes for measuring
but I don't think they had limited to sizes in terms of
the all the types of vessels they would use. No. I don't
think so. Okay let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So
תנא. tana. So the גמרא Gemara skips the whole first part of
the משנה mishnah we thought. הפשטן וניתוחן שוין בזר. hefshatan u'nituachan shavin
b'zar. So as opposed to just the simple sense of the משנה
Mishna which means that the slaying and the division was not sort
of done with the פייס payis, and it was just an ad
hoc distribution, ad hoc, the גמרא Gemara says it means more than
that. It means that they could be flayed and dismembered even with
a non כהן. kohen. It wasn't עבודה. avodah. So even so okay.
So אמר חזקיה. Amar Chizkiyah. So that's now we're going to focus
on this issue about what can be done בזר. b'zar. If it's
done בזר b'zar where would it be flayed? So that's a good
point like would you allow a זר zar in the עזרה, azarah,
in the עזרת כהנים? ezrat kohanim? You would. You might. There's an
issue about והזר הקרב אל המזבח. v'hazar hakarev el hamizbeach. You know,
but that's but in theory I mean a זר zar could be
in the as long as it's not going to the מזבח. mizbeach.
Yeah. It's a good point. A זר zar certainly could be in
the עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. You could do the הפשט וניתוח hefshet
u'nituach in עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. Of course it'll get a little
messy there. There was a special space to do it like. And
wasn't it right after? Yeah, after they slaughtered it right then they
exactly and they put them on a hook. Right. And as you
might remember in terms of the way the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
looked, right, if you have here your בית המקדש, Beis hamikdash right,
if here's whatever, right, so this area here, right, did they have
the holes for like for holding them and slaughtering them then they've
got the tables for washing out the innards and then they have
like the hooks here for hanging them up and flaying them? And
it was all done there. And Michael is right because the עזרת
ישראל Ezrat Yisrael was here, technically it was all the עזרה. azarah.
So In theory you could do it here without taking it חוץ
לעזרה chutz la'Azara but the actual stuff was done there but in
theory you could. Okay, what time of day was it done? What?
Well, the תמיד Tamid was first thing in the morning and the
תמיד tamid, in the afternoon was done very late in the afternoon.
Okay, the משנה Mishna in כלים Keilim that says, let me just
quickly answer this, the משנה Mishna, in כלים Keilim that talks about
who could be in the different zones in the מקדש Mikdash does
not... but we learned before the רגלים regalim that the whole place
was full of Jews. Yeah, well that's true too. Yeah, that's true
too. So yeah, so there would be times when they would go
in. Right, absolutely. And there's even a gate that was called the
Women's Gate of the עזרה. Azara. So the women would even go
in. It's... I mean the idea that only כהנים kohanim. can come
in is just... right, not really accurate. Right, right, right. Let me
just read it to you and then we'll go on. Okay, so...
here. It says, it talks about different areas of the מקדש Mikdash
and who could go in and it says עזרת הכהנים מקודשת מעזרת
ישראל, Ezrat ha-Kohanim mekudeshet me-Ezrat Yisrael, the עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim is
more sanctified than the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, שאין ישראל נכנסים לשם
אלא בשעת צרכיהם. she-ein Yisrael nichnasim le-sham ela b'shat tzorcheihem. They could
only go in when necessary. לסמיכה ולשחיטה ולתנופה. li-smicha u-li-shchita u-li-tnufa. Now
the normal necessary is I'm bringing my קרבן, korban. I want to
do סמיכה, smicha, maybe I even want to שחט shacht my own
קרבן korban, or a waving, but it does say that they could
go in as necessary into the עזרת כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. Okay, let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנא הפשט וניתוח שווין בזר.
Tana: hafshat u-nituach shavin be-zar. They could actually be done with a
non-כהן.
kohen. אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiya, מניין להפשט וניתוח ששוה בזר? Minayin le-hafshat
u-nituach she-shaveh be-zar? How do you know that the flay could be
again the phrase equal is borrowed from the משנה, Mishna? but how
do you know it could be done with a זר? zar? שנאמר,
she-ne'emar, the verse says ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח, ve-natnu
bnei Aharon ha-kohen esh al ha-mizbe'ach,
they should put fire on the altar.
So נתינת אש בכהונה, netinat esh bi-khuna, so
the fire requires a כהן. kohen. הפשט וניתוח לא בכהונה, hafshat u-nituach
lo bi-khuna, not the flaying and dismembering. Of course that's like a
strange לימוד limud because how do you know what you're excluding, why
is the suggested thing that is not being said about the flaying.
It says the fire needs כהנים, kohanim, so something else doesn't need
כהנים kohanim and we've identified that something else as the flaying and
dismemberment. So now we're going to spend the rest of today's דף
daf trying to figure, sort of doing an analysis of the פסוקים
psukim to try to get us to how we know that what
it's saying doesn't need כהן, kohen. the implicit thing that's being excluded
is the flaying and dismemberment. Is it possible that שווין shavin doesn't
mean equal, is it possible it means like
לעשות la'asot or נעשים, na'asim, נעשו? na'asu?
I don't think so. We'll talk about it later. Okay. המיבעי ליה,
Ha-mibaye leh, so the גמרא Gemara says המיבעי ליה לגופיה, ha-mibaye leh
le-gufeh, one minute, maybe for... there's two questions. One is how do
you know it's coming to exclude anything? And the other question is
how do you know what's being excluded? So the first question is
how do you know it's excluding anything? Maybe it's just telling you
that you need a כהן kohen. to put the wood on the
fire, to put the
wood on the altar,
maybe it's not an actual עבודה avoda of the
קרבן, korban so it's telling you
that this is considered an עבודה avoda and you need a כהן.
kohen, So אמר רב שימי בר אשי,
Amar Rav Shimi
bar Ashi, אשכחיה אביי, ashkachei Abaye, so now we're going to answer
the question based on a... this is a fascinating thing. אביי Abaye
teaches his son. Okay, so אשכחיה אביי דהוה מסבר ליה לבריה, ashkachei
Abaye de-hava masbar leh li-breh, I found אביי Abaye he was explaining
this to his son, how we get this idea that the הפשט
וניתוח hafshat u-nituach does not require a כהן. kohen Let's take a
look. ושחט. Ve-shachat. So actually it's important to read this פסוק pasuk
here because we're going to be focusing a lot on this פסוק.
pasuk. Okay. אם עלה קרבנו מן הבקר זכר תמים יקריבנו אל פתח
אהל מועד יקריב אתו לרצנו לפני ה'. Im ola korbano min ha-bakar
zachar tamim yakrivenu el petach ohel mo'ed yakriv oto li-rtzono lifnei Hashem.
וסמך ידו על ראש העלה ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. Ve-samach yado al
rosh ha-ola ve-nirtza lo le-khaper alav. So from this is וסמך ידו
ve-samach yado obviously it's
the בעלים, be'alim, owners, על ראש העלה.
al
rosh ha-ola. Okay, that's one פסוק. pasuk. The next פסוק pasuk is
ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה'. ve-shachat et ben ha-bakar lifnei Hashem.
ושחט. ve-shachat. Okay, את בן הבקר. et ben ha-bakar. And then what
does it say next Michael? והקריבו בני אהרן הכהנים את הדם. Ve-hikrivu
bnei Aharon ha-Kohanim et ha-dam. Okay. והקריבו בני אהרן, הכהנים את הדם,
vehikrivu benei Aharon hakohanim et hadam. וזרקו את הדם על המזבח סביב.
ve-zarku et ha-dam al ha-mizbe'ach saviv. Okay. Then והפשיט את העלה ונתח
אותה לנתחיה. ve-hifshit et ha-ola ve-nitach ota li-ntacheha. והפשיט. ve-hifshit.
What do you notice different about והפשיט? ve-hifshit? Singular again.
A singular, right? את העלה ונתח. et ha-ola ve-nitach. Okay, singular. Not
והקריבו בני אהרן. Ve-hikrivu bnei Aharon, Then ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש
על המזבח.
ve-natnu bnei Aharon ha-kohen
esh al ha-mizbe'ach.
So notice this...
ונתנו בני אהרן, ve-natnu bnei Aharon, right? ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש
על המזבח.
ve-natnu
bnei
Aharon ha-kohen esh al ha-mizbe'ach. בני אהרן הכהן אש, Benei Aharon hakohen
esh, right? וערכו Ve'archu what was it? העצים ha'etzim העצים ha'etzim וערכו
העצים על האש. Ve'archu ha'etzim al ha'esh. Okay,
so ונתנו. Venatnu.
ונתנו וערכו בני
אהרן,
Venatnu ve'archu
benei Aharon, okay?
So it's very... what? פשוט. Pashut. ויקרא Vayikra אלף alef starting with
דלת, dalet, okay?
So here it is, וזרקו, Ve'zarku, right? והקריבו, Vehikrivu, most cases it
says בני אהרן. Benei Aharon. ונתנו בני אהרן. Venatnu benei Aharon. וערכו
בני אהרן. Ve'archu benei Aharon. So what are the things that are
singular and are not בני אהרן? benei Aharon? סמיכה, Semicha, שחיטה, shechita,
הפשט ונתוח, hefshet venituach, right? Very good read of the פסוק, pasuk,
right? והקריב Vehikriv later though, because והקריב הכהן את הכל המזבחה. Vehikriv
hakohen et hakol hamizbecha. That's a problem. What? That's singular also but
it says הכהן hakohen though. No, והקריב הכהן את הכל המזבחה. Vehikriv
hakohen et hakol hamizbecha. Yeah, but it says הכהן. hakohen. Okay, but
והקריב הכהן את הכל המזבחה, Vehikriv hakohen et hakol hamizbecha, so maybe
that could also be done by a זר? zar? Okay, but it
pretty much always says הכהנים hakohanim when it's the כהנים. I think
only one place does וזרקו vezarku say הכהנים? hakohanim? No, but it's
the end of the פסוק pasuk of והקריבו. vehikrivu. So every time
it's the כהנים, it pretty much says it, okay? And otherwise, it
implies the בעלים ba'alim either by implicitly having been talked about the
בעלים ba'alim above, or by the shift to the singular. Okay, so
let's take a look. So in a way, it's going to be
funny because there's going to be a lot of like מדרש, midrash,
you know, like sort of דרשנ'ינג darshaning the פסוקים psukim in terms
to get to this conclusion, when in a way it's almost פשט
pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, אשכחיה אביי Ashkachei Abaye so I found אביי Abaye
דהוה מתני ליה לבריה: dahavei matni lei livreih: שחיטה בזר כשרה. Shechita
bezar keshera. The זר, zar, the owner שוחטס. shochets. That's okay. מנין
פשיטא? Maniyan pshita? So where are you coming from? Meaning, what would
have made you think that it wouldn't be okay? Obviously, we're starting
with an assumption that everything needs a כהן kohen. and we have
to be told that it doesn't need a כהן, kohen. which is
a pretty good assumption. But where's that assumption coming from? So מכלל
שנאמר mikhla shenemar because of the general statement in the פסוק pasuk
ואתם ובניכם אתך
תשמרו את כהנתכם,
ve'atem uvenayich
itcha
tishmru et kehunatchem, you have to protect your כהונה, kehuna, והזר הקרב
יומת. vehazar hakarev yumat.
So basically it says, hey, this is yours, everybody else off limits.
So the assumption is anything relating to the בית המקדש service is
a כהן. kohen. שומע אני אפילו שחיטה, Shomea ani afilu shechita, so
maybe that includes even שחיטה? shechita? תלמוד לומר ושחט את בן הבקר
לפני ה' talmud lomar veshachat et ben habakar lifnei Hashem and then
והקריבו בני אהרן ve-hikrivu bnei Aharon. הכהנים את הדם. ha-Kohanim et ha-dam,
מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה, Mekabala va'eilach mitzvat kehuna, from the catching of
the דם, dam, that's where the כהנים jump in. Because although it
says והקריבו, vehikrivu, which means to bring the דם dam to the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, remember we even had the discussion before about the פייס,
payis? who was the מקבל mekabel of the דם. dam. And the
guy who's the מקבל mekabel is the one who is the... who
is bringing the דם dam to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So this is,
this is קבלה kabbalah and הקרבה. hakrabah. So this is שחיטה shechita
and the four עבודות, avodahs, right? And this is זריקה. zrika. So
starting with קבלה kabbalah and הקרבה hakrabah gets wrapped into והקריבו. vehikrivu.
So starting with קבלה, kabbalah, that's the עבודה avodah that requires a
כהן. kohen. שחיטה Shechita does not require a כהן. kohen. Okay, וסמך
ידו ושחט vesamach yado veshachat going back to the פסוק, pasuk, he
the owner סמיכה smicha and he שוחט, shochet, לימד על השחיטה שכשרה
בזר. lilmed al hashechita shekeshera bezar. So a זר zar can do
the שחיטה. shechita. Very good, that gets us there. How about the
סמיכה? smicha? Because he not only can, he have to do the
סמיכה, smicha, it's his קרבן. korban Now how are we going to
get to the הפשט ונתוח, hefshet venituach, that that can be a
זר? zar? מכדי, Mikhdi, let's take a look. מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה.
Mekabala va'eilach mitzvat kehuna. ונתנו בני אהרן Venatnu benei Aharon למה לי?
lama li? So why then does the פסוק pasuk down here have
to re-emphasize... it already said בני אהרן, benei Aharon, right? וזרקו vezarku
is the end of this פסוק. pasuk. Why, so I know that
the general rule is only כהנים unless I'm told otherwise. And then
I'm told this is okay, not from here כהנים kick in. If
from here כהנים kick in, why does it have to repeat בני
אהרן benei Aharon here? I've already been told it's כהנים. I'm going
to assume everything that follows is כהנים and you know what? That's
like a you know, a פשט pshat question in the פסוקים. psukim.
בני אהרן, Benei Aharon, בני אהרן, benei Aharon, בני אהרן, benei Aharon,
I got the idea, right? It's the כהנים here are doing the
עבודה. avodah. So why is it repeating בני אהרן? benei Aharon? So
what's the obvious answer? Because this פסוק pasuk is not בני אהרן,
benei Aharon, because the הפשט ונתוח hefshet venituach is not בני אהרן.
benei Aharon. And therefore it has to go back to tell you
בני אהרן. benei Aharon. And that's what we were talking about, that
הפשט ונתוח hefshet venituach is בזר, bezar, yeah. So למה לי? lama
li? So מכדי מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה. mikhdi mekabala va'eilach mitzvat kehuna.
ונתנו בני אהרן Venatnu benei Aharon למה לי? lama li? Why does
it have to go back and say בני אהרן? benei Aharon? It's
already all about כהנים. למעוטי הפשט ונתוח, Lemu'atei hefshet venituach, to tell
you that the flaying and the dismembering, that does not have to
be בני אהרן. benei Aharon. Okay, that's what אביי Abaye explained to
his son. Beautiful, פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim. So now the
גמרא Gemara is going to have a lot of questions. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: הכתי אצטריך, Hakti itztarich, one minute, you
can't tell me that. It had to say בני אהרן benei Aharon
there for a particular purpose. What's the purpose it had to tell
me that by the... by the putting the... fire on the altar.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I would have thought כיון דלאו
עבודה דמעכב כפרה היא, keivan d'lav avoda d'ma'akev kapara hee, that's not
an עבודה avoda that prevents the animal from being kosher, it's not
the כפרה, kapara, it's not the קבלה kabala or the זריקה, zrika,
maybe it's of a different quality and therefore לא בעי כהונה, lo
ba'ee kehuna, maybe it wouldn't require כהן. kohen, קא משמע לן דבעי
כהונה, ka mashma lan d'ba'ee kehuna, it does require כהן. kohen. So
therefore you can't learn it from here. Now what is going on?
Because while the simple thing that אביי Abaye is saying is very
clear, כהן, kohen if he doesn't point out a singular כהן kohen
again, so obviously it's leapfrogging over this to tell you non-כהן. kohen.
The גמרא Gemara is not looking at it that way. The גמרא
Gemara is looking at it in its classic sort of דרשה drasha
way of this is an extra פסוק, pasuk, what do we learn
from the extra פסוק? pasuk? So ignore everything that came above. Just
have this one little פסוק pasuk that says ונתנו בני אהרן אש
על המזבח. v'natnu bnei Aharon esh al hamizbe'ach. Oh, that's superfluous. I
know כהנים do the עבודה. avoda. So the only reason תורה's Torah
telling me that is to imply that there's something else that doesn't
need a כהן. kohen. So then the answer to that is it's
not superfluous. I might have thought that since this isn't actually the
הקרבת הקרבן, hakravat hakorban, maybe it didn't have to be a כהן.
kohen. So it's not superfluous. So therefore it's not superfluous, you can't
infer anything. Again, what I would say he really is inferring is
not the fact that it's superfluous but that it leapfrogs and that
this is the singular and it's בני אהרן Bnei Aharon before and
after. But the גמרא Gemara is understanding it to be from the
fact that it's superfluous it's teaching me that this doesn't need a
כהן, kohen and it's saying it's not superfluous because maybe I wouldn't
have thought... maybe that also wouldn't have required כהן. kohen, Okay, so
we're still... so we feel we still don't have our לימוד limud
about the הפשט וניתוח. hafshot v'nituach. So you learn from this אביי
Abaye was Sephardic and the גמרא Gemara is Ashkenaz. Alrighty. So it
says like this. It's going to be interesting אביי's Abaye's seeing אביי
Abaye in terms of him teaching issues related to קרבנות. It's going
to come up more later on. Anyway, let's take a look. אלא
מהכא. Ela meihacha. Right. There you go. אלא מהכא. Ela meihacha. So
let's try from here. וערכו בני אהרן הכהנים את הנתחים את הראש
ואת הפדר. v'archu bnei Aharon hakohanim et hanetachim et harosh v'et hapader.
So it's וערכו. v'archu. No, not that וערכו את העצים, v'archu et
ha'etzim, another וערכו. v'archu. Where is that? Where's this right after ונתנו?
v'natnu? וערכו את העצים על האש v'archu et ha'etzim al ha'esh וערכו
בני אהרן הכהנים את הנתחים את הראש ואת הפדר. v'archu bnei Aharon
hakohanim et hanetachim et harosh v'et hapader. So it's this two וערכו's
v'archu next to each other. I see, okay. That's וערכו את העצים
v'archu et ha'etzim and then there's וערכו v'archu right? את הנתחים. et
hanetachim. That's putting the stuff actually on the fire. Right? And that
says בני אהרן, Bnei Aharon, right? Yes. Okay, so that. Okay, so
that also is seen as extra. Once we know here that even
though it's not about the bringing of the קרבן, you know, I
might have thought it doesn't require כהן. kohen? And the גמרא Gemara
is saying, no, it's telling me בני אהרן Bnei Aharon even after...
even if it's not about the bringing of the קרבן you need
a כהן. kohen. So then this בני אהרן Bnei Aharon is again
extra. If the fire already needs a כהן, kohen certainly the putting
of the limbs on the altar is going to need a כהן.
kohen. So now at least we got something else that's extra. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא מהכא וערכו בני אהרן
הכהנים את הנתחים את הראש ואת הפדר. Ela meihacha v'archu bnei Aharon
hakohanim et hanetachim et harosh v'et hapader. מכדי מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה.
Michdi mikabala v'eilach mitzvat kehuna. From קבלה kabala onward it's a כהן's
kohen. job. וערכו למה לי? v'archu lama lee? So why does it
have to tell me again that the כהן kohen puts the limbs
on? Okay. So it must be למיעוטי הפשט וניתוח l'miyuti hafshot v'nituach
to tell me that those are the things that require כהנים but
not the flaying, not the dismembering. So, what do you mean? He'd
say the same thing he said. No, that's what the גמרא Gemara
says... according to אביי Abaye it's the two בני אהרן Bnei Aharon
that's already seen that, you know... Well, some people want to learn
that this is all אביי Abaye saying to his son, that... that
אביי Abaye is working this through with his son. I don't think
that's what's going on. I think אביי Abaye said the first thing
and the גמרא Gemara is reframing it. Anyway, ואימא... v'eima... so now
the גמרא Gemara says fine, here it says בני אהרן, Bnei Aharon,
that's extra, that teaches you that that פסוק pasuk does not require
a כהן. kohen So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא למיעוטי שני גזירי
עצים? v'eima l'miyuti shnei gizirei etzim? No, maybe what it's telling me
is that this stuff here requires כהנים but the two logs of
wood in the afternoon תמיד, tamid. that doesn't require כהן. kohen Now
that's like, where are you getting that from? Like that's not even
part of the whole conversation. Okay. And especially since the wood here
requires כהנים, it's strange why I would think the afternoon wood would
not require כהן. kohen So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going
to respond back. מסתברא דביחא דכוותיה קממעיט. Mistabra divcha d'chvatah ka m'ma'et.
It makes sense that it's excluding a קרבן issue, not like wood.
Okay. What I would say even stronger is it's excluding something in
this process. Okay, the one that doesn't say כהן kohen and the
one that's in singular. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara is saying that
makes sense that that's what it's saying, that that part doesn't need
כהנים. The גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, Adaraba, no, I'll say the opposite.
סידרא דכוותיה ממעיט. Sidra d'chvatah m'ma'et. Since this is talking about putting
things on the fire, so this putting things on the fire requires
כהנים. But there's another putting things on the fire that does not,
the wood in the afternoon... the wood by the afternoon תמיד. tamid,
Okay. So you see that rather than like just looking at the
פסוק... pasuk... and looking at the difference of this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
it's all based on this דרשה *derasha* of if it's an extra
thing, what is it coming to exclude? So maybe it's excluding something
in a completely different category. Excluding the wood that's put in the
afternoon. לא סלקא דעתך *lo salka da'atach*, that doesn't make sense. דאמר
מר *de'amar mar*, because the master teaches, והקריב הכהן את הכל המזבחה
*vehikriv hakohen et hakol hamizbecha*, the *kohen* shall bring it all to
the altar, זו הולכת איברים לכבש *zu holachat evarim lakevesh*. This is
the bringing of the limbs to the ramp. הולכת איברים לכבש הוא
דבעי כהונה *holachat evarim lakevesh hu de'ba'i kehuna*. So that requires a
*kohen*, bringing the limbs to the ramp. הולכת עצים etzim. לא בעי
כהונה *holachat etzim lo ba'i kehuna*. And then very interesting, but implicitly
the bringing of the wood to the ramp would not require a
*kohen*, because it's only the bringing of the limbs that the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is telling us. הסידור שני גזירי עצים shnei geizirei eitzim,
*hasidur shenei gezeirei etzim*, and then implicit from that is that only
the bringing, the bringing of the wood does not require כהנים *kohanim*,
but the actual placing of the wood בעי כהונה *ba'i kehuna* does
require *kohen*. So that's a little bit funny how it makes all
those inferences by what's not being said. But the basic answer is
no, we're taking it for granted that putting of the wood on
the altar, whether in the morning or actually, excuse me, I said
the morning, I didn't mean it, this is just an עולה *olah*,
this is just a private עולה *olah*. But whether the putting on
the wood on the altar, whether in this category or whether in
whether or whether in the afternoon תמיד tamid *Tamid*, we're taking it
for granted that that requires a *kohen*. So if that requires a
*kohen*, right, why does it say בני אהרן Bnei Aharon *benei Aharon*
here? What does it coming, I knew that we're talking about כהנים
*kohanim*, from this point on I know we're talking about כהנים *kohanim*,
why does it repeat בני אהרן Bnei Aharon *benei Aharon*? And it
must be repeating it to tell me that this does not require
כהנים *kohanim*. Okay, וערכו למה לי *ve'archu lama li*? What? The which
does not require? הפשט Hafshet וניתוח *hefshet venituach*. Okay. So when you
say that that's the most interesting part. Yeah, it is, it's giving
the non-כהנים *kohanim* the dirty work. Totally. Okay, because maybe they don't
want to do it. Exactly, and that's the one thing. Okay. But
at the end of the day, it's pretty פשט *pshat* of the
פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וערכו למה לי *ve'archu lama li*? So why
again do I need וערכו בני אהרן Bnei Aharon *ve'archu benei Aharon*
here את הנתחים *et hanetachim*? Once I know that anyway all this
stuff is with כהנים *kohanim*. למיעוטי הפשט וניתוח *lemi'utei hefshet venituach* to
exclude הפשט וניתוח *hefshet venituach* doesn't require כהנים *kohanim*. So again, okay,
we're back to the pretty simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* somehow still not satisfied. ואימא הכא נמי
לגופיה *ve'eima hacha nami legufia*? Maybe I need this to tell me
something about it itself. Now what I need it to tell me
about it itself is not clear because we've already said it's obvious
that it needs כהנים *kohanim*. But we're going to see in a
minute what why it might be emphasizing בני אהרן Bnei Aharon. *benei
Aharon* here for a purpose intrinsic to the placing of the limbs
on the altar. So maybe it's not extra. We'll see why it's
not extra in a minute. אלא בהאי *ela behai*. Here's how we
learn it out. והקריב הכהן את הכל *vehikriv hakohen et hakol*, where
it says the *kohen* puts it all up, where's that פסוק *pasuk*?
I might have gave you that a minute ago, right? וערכו את
הנתחים ובקרבו ירחץ והקטיר את הכל *ve'archu et hanetachim u'vekirbo yirchatz vehiktir
et hakol*. So, okay, I'm sorry, let's just continue here. So what
is it? וקרבו וכרעיו ירחץ והקטיר הכהן את הכל *u'kirbo u'khra'av yirchatz
vehiktir hakohen et hakol*. Okay, so this is הכל *hakol*, this is
basically the placing of the נתחים *netachim* on the fire. Okay. And
this includes even the קרביים *kirbayim*, right? Remember we discussed the limbs
with so many כהנים *kohanim*, the קרביים *kirbayim* with so many. Okay,
so this is the קרביים *kirbayim*. This is the putting on the
fire. Okay, so again the question is why הכהן *hakohen* here? That's
extra. So you have to be all the way up on top
of the כבש kevesh *kevesh* on top of the מזבח Mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*.
What? Yeah. Okay. אלא *ela*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והקריב
הכהן את הכל המזבחה *vehikriv hakohen et hakol hamizbecha*, so first it's
bringing it to the ramp and then you're going to put it
on the altar. So הולכת איברים לכבש הוא דבעי כהונה *holachat evarim
lakevesh hu de'ba'i kehuna*. הולכת עצים לא בעי כהונה *holachat etzim lo
ba'i kehuna*. Okay, so so well so it's bringing it, so we're
repeating what we said before. Right. It's bringing the limbs to the
ramp that requires a *kohen*, not the bringing of the wood. הסידור
שני גזירי עצים shnei gizeirei eitzim בעי כהונה *hasidur shenei gezeirei etzim
ba'i kehuna*. So the putting of the of the logs requires a
*kohen*. ונתנו לגופיה *venatnu legufia* where it says ונתנו בני אהרן Bnei
Aharon *venatnu benei Aharon*. That's coming to tell you that that is
again even though it's not part of making it a כשר קרבן
*kasher korban*, it's still requires כהנים *kohanim*. וערכו *ve'archu*, and now the
וערכו *ve'archu* here, okay, why do you need the בני אהרן *benei
Aharon* here by the וערכו *ve'archu* by the putting of the limbs?
Now we're going to tell you what you need it for. וערכו
שנים *ve'archu shenayim*, because that's in the plural, that's two. בני אהרן
שנים *benei Aharon shenayim*, two. הכהנים שנים *hakohanim shenayim*, two. למדנו לתמיד
שטונה ששה *lamadnu le'tamid she'teuna shisha*. So this whole thing about dividing
up the תמיד tamid, *Tamid* between six כהנים *kohanim* bringing the limbs
and then three plurals tells me six Kohanim are the ones that
bring the limbs to the ramp and then put it, you know,
from the ramp onto the onto the altar. Okay. So anyway, למדנו
לתשעה דהוו שיתא, so so okay so one minute. So now, so
that we're not done though because אמר רב המנונא. Amar Rav Hamnuna.
That's very nice, except there's a little problem. קשיא ליה לרבי אלעזר.
Kashya lei le-Rabbi Elazar. Rabbi Elazar had a problem with that little
drasha. האי בבן הבקר כתיב. Hai be-ven ha-bakar ktiv. This pasuk is
talking about a cow, not a sheep! And a cow we just
learned is twenty-four, so you can't say that these doubles here are
coming to tell you the thing about the sheep. ובן הבקר עשרים
וארבעה בעי. U-ven ha-bakar esrim v'arba'ah ba'ei. וניחא ליה, V'nicha lei, he
resolved it because it says על העצים אשר על האש אשר על
המזבח Al ha-etzim asher al ha-esh asher al ha-mizbe'ach that you put
these limbs on the fire, on the wood, on the altar, which
is a little like redundant, right, to say all those things? So
איזהו דבר שנאמר בו עצים אש ומזבח? Eizehu davar she-ne'emar bo etzim
esh u-mizbe'ach? What type of Korban does it mention all these things,
fire, wood, and limbs? הוי אומר זה טלה, Hevei omer zeh taleh,
the Tamid, because the Tamid the Torah says, you know, אש על
המזבח תוקד בו לא תכבה, Esh al ha-mizbe'ach tukad bo lo tichbeh,
וביער עליה הכהן עצים בבוקר בבוקר. U-vi'er aleha ha-Kohen etzim ba-boker ba-boker.
So the whole idea of Esh and Mizbe'ach and Etzim is all
mentioned with the Tamid. Okay, so basically what we are what we
have finished with, it's a little unclear how the Gemara finally resolved,
but the basic point is that again, it's here all the Kohanim
plural, Kohanim plural, no Kohanim, הפשט and ניתוח Nituach is bizarre. Gemara
says is it based on the fact that בני אהרן it's just
simply p'shat of the psukim, but Gemara wants to base it on
the fact that בני אהרן is extra. So it says it's not
really extra here, you need to emphasize that you need Kohanim even
when it's not actually making the Korban a kosher Korban, but בני
אהרן might be seen as extra here coming to tell you that
this does not need it to be בני אהרן. But the final
drasha of the Gemara was maybe part of what בני אהרן is
doing here is this teaching that you get six Kohanim to put
the stuff on the מזבח. mizbe-ach. Okay, let's move on from that.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, we're not really moving on, זר
שסידר את המערכה חייב. Zar she-sider et ha-ma'aracha chayav. If a non-Kohen
put, we'd said right, that this has to be the putting of
the fire, the putting of the wood has to be a Kohen.
If a non-Kohen did it, חייב, chayav, he transgresses, he's a non-Kohen
that did an עבודה avodah and he's חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav
misah bidei shamayim. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? What will he
what can he do now to correct himself? פורקה וחוזר וסודרה. Porkah
v'chozer v'sodrah. He takes it off the fire and puts it back
on. So the Gemara says: What? מאי אהני ליה? Mai ahani lei?
What good does it do for him to put it back on?
He when he puts it on it's no good, he's just going
to do the עבירה aveira a second time. It's like you know,
you walk into a room and you turn off turn on the
light, you forgot it's Shabbos, what do you do, it's Shabbos, oh
whoops, and you turn it back off. So that's actually going to
help? Makes it worse! So מאי אהני ליה? Mai ahani lei? אלא
פורקה זר וסודרה כהן. Ella porkah zar v'sodrah Kohen. Fine, he undoes
it, and then a Kohen will come and do it. He did
his עבירה, aveira, but you can redo the putting of the wood
on the fire, take it down and a Kohen will put it
back on. Yeah, well how do you learn that? Was there a
Gemara didn't want to explore, couldn't make sense of, was a mistake,
that's not what he meant? Like they just completely erase what he
said? Like, I don't know. No, it could be implicit, it could
be he's not emphasizing the זר, zar, he's more saying how you
deal with the situation is you undo it and you redo it,
you know, as opposed to this person. But anyway, I should by
the way say, I'm being a little imprecise, because סידור מערכה Siddur
Ma'aracha is not it's not עצים. סידור מערכה Siddur Ma'aracha is וערכו
עצים, V'archu etzim, it's like arranging the woodpile, you know, with the
stuff that's already there. And then there's the act of adding new
wood. Because it says וערכו בני אהרן עצים על המזבח V'archu Bnei
Aharon etzim al ha-mizbe'ach ונתנו עצים על האש. V'natnu etzim al ha-esh.
So those are two stages. One is organizing it and the other
is putting the new wood. Here it's talking just the אריכה, aricha,
just the setting up of the woodpile has to be done by
a Kohen. If it's done by a זר, zar, you undo it
and then it's redone by a Kohen. So you're saying if he
doesn't end up burning it after the עבודה avodah starts, then it
doesn't do anything? Right, what one more time, what are you saying?
Taking it apart, look, you've already done it, right, but what does
it help to take it apart? It tells in the case that
there's an act of אריכה aricha that's important to be done by
a Kohen. Well, no, in the case that the אריכה aricha is
nothing until it ultimately gets burnt and then retroactively that אריכה aricha
becomes... Oh, okay, maybe. I hear that, I hear that. I also
think is the חידוש chiddush is you might think עריכה arichah stuff
like it needs to be arranged, have it arranged, you know? So
if a זר zar did it, he did his sin, but now
nothing needs to be done. Right, exactly, but it is. No, but
that’s the point, the point is that there’s an actual act of
עריכה arichah that is important to be done by a כהן, kohen,
even if like not necessarily in a way, so you make it.
That’s, that’s but I hear your point as well. Okay, so wait,
so you’re saying that when we mean the 18, not bringing it
on, that we conclude it needed a כהן? kohen, Yeah, everything needs
a כהן. kohen And that’s what he’s saying. So, yeah, to just
say what I would have excluded from the פסוק but in the
end I didn’t. In the end, the bringing, you know, only the
bringing of the 18 to the ramp doesn't need a כהן kohen.
but the putting the 18 on the, yeah, yeah, that doesn’t. Okay,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רב ביבי בר
אביי Mative Rav Beivai bar Abaye Rav Beivai asks, is there an
עבודה avodah that’s כשרה בלילה ksherah balaylah and פסולה בזר? psulah bezar?
One minute. You're telling me that the עריכה, arichah, now again, we've
learned it very nicely from the פסוקים pesukim that the עריכה arichah
requires a כהן. kohen, But I don't get it, he says. This
is a nighttime עבודה. avodah. This would take place, you know, you'd
do it at the end of the day, I don't know, no,
you'd do it at the end of the day, you'd do it
together with the תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, which would be the beginning
of the day, I should say. So you would do it at
night. So if it’s something that's night, he says, it’s not a
real עבודה. avodah. So if it’s not a real עבודה avodah that
could be done at night, then I don't see why a זר
zar can’t do it, even though the פסוקים pesukim suggest otherwise, I
don't see why the זר zar can't do it if it can
be done at night. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולו? velo? Is
that really true? I'll show you plenty of עבודות avodot that are
done at night that need a כהן. kohen והרי איברים ופדרים, ve-harei
evarim u-fedarim, how about the burning of the limbs? That means a
כהן kohen and that gets finished at night. The גמרא Gemara says,
סוף עבודת יממא היא, sof avodat yemama hi, that’s fundamentally a day
עבודה, avodah, but if you didn’t finish burning them on the fire
in the day, you finish at night. But fundamentally it’s a day
עבודה. avodah. As opposed to this, which he understands, it’s like setting
up the fire in the first thing in the morning, or first
thing before the morning began, is fundamentally a night עבודה. avodah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, והרי תרומת הדשן, ve-harei trumat hadeshen, how
about the removing of the ashes? That’s done before daybreak and that’s
פסול בזר. pasul bezar. The גמרא Gemara says, תחילת עבודת יממא היא.
tchilat avodat yemama hi. Fine, that’s starting the day עבודה. avodah. It
relates to what’s going to be done in the day. It’s not
fundamentally a night עבודה. avodah. Of course, our response would be, but
that’s exactly what the עריכה arichah of the wood is, right? It’s
done at the time of the תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, it’s to
get the fire ready for the day. So why he thinks תרומת
הדשן trumat hadeshen can be assigned the label of day עבודה avodah
and not the wood, I really don’t know. So the גמרא Gemara
says, דאמר רבי אפטוריקי אמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rabi Aptoriki amar Rabi
Yochanan, here’s the evidence that the תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen is considered
to be a day עבודה avodah even though it takes place at
night: קידש ידיו לתרומת הדשן למחר אינו צריך לקדש kidesh yadav litrumat
hadeshen lemachar eino tzarich lekadesh if a כהן kohen washes his hands
for תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, he doesn't have to wash his hands
at daybreak, שכבר קידש מתחילת עבודה. shekevar kidesh mitchilat avodah. Because normally
you wash your hands at daybreak when it passes from night to
day, but here you don’t have to because you already did it
for the day עבודות avodot and therefore this was the first of
the day עבודות avodot and you already washed your hands for that.
So you see it’s considered to be the first of the day
עבודות. avodot. But somehow, maybe the understanding is just the תרומת הדשן
trumat hadeshen part of it, not the מערכה. ma'arachah. That is conceived
of as a pure night עבודה. avodah. And therefore he doesn’t understand
why a non-כהן kohen can’t do it. So, אלא קשיא. ela kashya.
So we’ve got our problem. So אלא כי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela
ki itamar hachi itamar, here’s how it was said: אמר רבי אפטוריקי
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabi Aptoriki amar Rabi Yochanan, זר שסידר שני
גזירי עצים חייב. zar she-sider shenei gizeiri eitzim chayav. הוה ליה עבודת
יום. hava lei avodat yom. Actually, we're going to say that he’s
not talking about סידור המערכה sidur hamarachah which is the first part,
ערכו עצים על האש. archu eitzim al ha-esh. He's talking about the
next part, ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח. venatnu benei Aharon
hakohen esh al hamizbe'ach. So if a non-כהן kohen is, one minute,
hold on, let me just make sure I'm saying this right. Yeah,
if a non-כהן Kohen. puts the two logs of wood on the
fire, that’s already an עבודת יום avodat yom and therefore you’re חייב.
chayav. So basically the גמרא Gemara has done an amazing thing. It
basically said that although we said we learn from the פסוקים pesukim
that this requires a כהן, Kohen. and we start out with a
simple statement which is that okay, it requires a כהן, Kohen, if
a non-כהן did it he’s חייב, chayav, he transgresses. Because of this
idea that we’re conceptualizing this as a nighttime עבודה, avodah, we basically
said it’s not true. If a זר zar did it, actually he
wouldn’t be חייב chayav even though the פסוקים pesukim, say כהן. If
a זר zar did it, he wouldn’t be חייב, chayav, it’s a
nighttime עבודה. avodah. When is a זר zar חייב? chayav? Only in
the putting of the logs on the wood, the new putting of
the logs, that’s already considered to be a daytime עבודה. avodah. But
the arranging of the logs, that’s conceived of as a nighttime עבודה.
avodah. And even though the פסוקים psukim tell you you need a
כהן, and even though initially we said a non-כהן is חייב, chayav,
because we’re conceptualizing it as a nighttime עבודה avodah and we’re assuming
that a nighttime עבודה avodah has to be כשרה בזר, ksherah bezar,
we’re actually saying the פסוקים, psukim? it’s not true, בדיעבד bedi'avad you
don’t need a כהן to do it. Okay, so if he said
anything, he didn’t say it about arranging the wood, he said it
about putting the new logs. of the wood on the fire. אלא
אמר הכי אמר רב אסי אמר רב יוחנן זר שסידר שני גזירי
עצים חייב הואיל ועבודת יום היא. Ela amar hachi amar Rav Assi
amar Yochanan zar shesidar shnei geizirei eitzim chayav, ho-il v'avodat yom hi.
Even though maybe that's done at night, like the תרומת הדשן trumat
hadeshen is done at night, that at least can be conceptualized as
an עבודת יום. avodat yom. So מתקיף לה רבא, matkif lah Rava,
so Rava asks on this, אלא מעתה תבעי פייס, ela me-ata tiba-i
payis, if it's really an עבודת יום, avodat yom, why don't you
do a lottery for that? So אשתמיטתיה, ishteimitati, so Rava forgot when
he asked this question, הא דתניא, ha ditanya, what we taught in
a ברייתא: braita: מי שזכה בתרומת הדשן זכה בסידור המערכה ובסידור שני
גזירי עצים. mi she-zacha bitrumat hadeshen zacha b'sidur hama-aracha u-v'sidur shnei geizirei
eitzim. There's a lottery for that. The guy who does the תרומת
הדשן trumat hadeshen also arranges the wood and puts on the logs
of wood. So fine, so that's what we have. So again, I
want to just make clear what we're saying, right? You've got here
the normal עבודה avodah is, if you remember the פייס, payis. right,
the פייס ראשון payis rishon was for תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, right,
and what happened? The guy who did the תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen
did the סידור מערכה, sidur ma-aracha, he arranged the wood pile, he
did the שני גזירי עצים, he put on the two logs, and
then he did the תרומת הדשן, trumat hadeshen, right, and then it
was דשון, dishun, and then you did the תמיד, tamid, right? So
that's what you did, right? So now the גמרא Gemara is saying
and even though all of this in the פסוקים pesukim, down here
say בני אהרון הכהנים, bnei Aharon hakohanim, right, requires כהנים, and we
start by saying therefore if a non-כהן does it he's חייב מיתה
chayav mitah because of this, of this challenge, oh, it's a nighttime
עבודה, avodah, we all of a sudden are now saying that this
is כשר בזר kasher b'zar against the פסוק because we're conceptualizing it
and against the original statement of רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan because we're
conceptualizing it as a nighttime עבודה. avodah. And what we're saying is
though this already is considered to be relating to the day. So
this part already is a day עבודה avodah and this part a
זר zar is חייב chayav but not the part, not the סידור
מערכה sidur ma-aracha that preceded it. So how would have us read
the פסוקים? pesukim If any of these עבודות avodot were done during
the day they would require כהנים presumably, you know, but what is
a סידור מערכה? sidur ma-aracha? It's, I don't know that it's arranging
the, you know, the stuff burns and you rearrange all the wood.
You ever tend to a campfire? There's a lot of סידור מערכה
sidur ma-aracha goes on in tending to a campfire. So the גמרא
Gemara goes like this: okay, so and רבא Rava says, why don't
you have a פייס? payis, And the answer is you do have
a פייס. payis Okay, so למימרא, l'meimra, the גמרא Gemara says, the
fact that רבא Rava said, one minute, if it's a day עבודה
avodah it needs to have a פייס, payis that means עבודות דבי
פייס, avodot d'bei payis, עבודת לילה לא בעי פייס, avodat laila lo
ba-ei payis, implicitly רבא Rava is saying that things that are daytime
עבודות avodot you do a פייס payis for, at least if they're
קרבן ציבור, nighttime עבודות avodot you don't do a פייס payis for.
והרי איברים ופדרים, v'harei eivarim u'fdarim, what about the burning of the
limbs? Now, I don't know where the גמרא Gemara, knows that the
burning of the limbs you did a פייס payis for, right? I
mean, what you did a פייס payis, for was the bringing up,
according to one position, you did a פייס payis. for the bringing
of the limbs from the כבש to the top of the מזבח.
Everybody remember that? The fourth פייס, payis the bringing of the limbs
from the ramp to the top of the altar? So that is
bringing it and putting it on the fire is then the burning
of the limbs. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ah, but that
and presumably that was the morning תמיד tamid and it was maybe
indeed and it was the afternoon תמיד, tamid? so maybe that burning
of the limbs had to be finished at night and nevertheless you're
doing a פייס. payis So look, you do a פייס payis on
something that applies at night. Now, that's such an obvious answer. The
גמרא Gemara says סוף עבודה דיממא היא. sof avodah d'yimama hi. What
are you talking about? That whole process begins in the day, right?
I mean, the basic פייס payis. there was for bringing, putting it
on the fire initially and that was done during the day. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והרי תרומת הדשן. v'harei trumat hadeshen.
I know, it's a very strange גמרא, Gemara, it's repeating itself. What
about the תרומת הדשן? trumat hadeshen? If רבא Rava is assuming that
you only do a פייס payis, for daytime עבודות, avodot, so the
תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen is a nighttime עבודה. avodah. Now there's an
obvious answer, what's the answer? What we said up before: תחילת עבודה
דיממא היא. tchilat avodah d'yimama hi. Bizarrely, the גמרא Gemara gives a
different answer. תוספות doesn't understand why it gives a different answer. The
גמרא Gemara says no, that's משום מעשה שהיה. mishum ma-aseh shehayah. That
was because of what happened. Remember what happened? The race and the
כהן breaking the leg and the other כהן getting stabbed. So okay,
so anyway now we are completely focusing on a different thing. Based
on רבא's Rava question, what is the assumption of what things you
do a lottery for? And there's an assumption you only do a
lottery for day עבודות, avodot, not night עבודות. avodot. So the גמרא
Gemara says למימרא דעבודת יום שזר חייב עליה מיתה בעי פייס. l'meimra
d'avodat yom she-zar chayav aleha mitah ba-ei payis. So now it seems
like we're coming to the conclusion, it's all about the lottery, that
day עבודות avodot and things that a זר zar is חייב chayav
for are things that need a פייס. payis אין זר חייב עליה
מיתה לא בעי פייס, ein zar chayav aleha mitah lo ba-ei payis,
but presumably if a זר zar is not חייב מיתה chayav mitah
for it, it would not need a פייס, payis right? So if
that's true says the גמרא, Gemara והרי שחיטה, v'harei shchitah, how about
שחיטה? shchitah? That was one of the things that was distributed and
that's כשר בזר. kasher b'zar. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני.
shani. שאני שחיטה דתחילת עבודה היא. shani shechita d'techilas avodah hee. Aye,
yeah, but that's the beginning of the process of the תמיד, tamid,
and the תמיד tamid. and all the rest of the processes need
a כהן. Okay. I say, wait, why does a זר zar want
to שחט shecht the תמיד? tamid. Could he? Is that it? If
a זר zar wants no, he could, and the גמרא Gemara even
said it before, although presumably not for the תמיד, but at least
hypothetically maybe he could. But it's just saying that that was included
in the פייס because it's all part of the פייס for the
תמיד. But if they knew there was always a זר zar that
was designated for that day, they wouldn't mind him, I don't know,
I don't know. So the גמרא Gemara says, דאנן לא תנן הכי,
d'anan lo tnan hachi, we didn't teach this way, because what did
we teach in the משנה? אמר להם הממונה צאו וראו אם הגיע
זמן השחיטה. amar lahem hamemuneh tze'u ur'u im higia zman hashechita. So
they had a guy looking out to see if it was daybreak
so you could שחט. shecht. ואילו זמן שני גזירי עצים לא קתני.
v'ilu zman shnei gizeirei eitzim lo katni. So, and the two logs
of wood you did not teach, meaning the גמרא's Gemara, understanding, and
this helps clarify it, that if we're saying this is a לילה
עבודה laila avodah and this is only considered to be a day
עבודה avodah because it's תחילת עבודה דיממא, techilas avodah d'yimama, so the
גמרא's Gemara understanding that the only reason we excluded the סידור המערכה
sidur hama'aracha is the only night thing that we're willing to say
is connected to the day is the תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen. That's
the only thing we've considered. So if that's true, what about the
logs of wood? Right? So why is that considered a day עבודה?
avodah? So the גמרא's actually assuming that this occurred during the day.
דף קפ״ה. Daf Kuf-peh-hei. So that's what the גמרא's assuming. We have
to make it a day עבודה avodah to be חייב chayav for
it, and therefore תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen is the only nighttime thing
that is considered a day עבודה, avodah, so that has to be
during the day. If that's true, says the גמרא, we didn't teach
that. We said when it's daybreak, it's the time for שחיטה. shechita.
ואילו זמן שני גזירי עצים לא קתני. v'ilu zman shnei gizeirei eitzim
lo katni. So, and we didn't say that it's the time for
the logs of wood. So you see the logs of wood could
be done at the night. The גמרא says, no. הך דלית ליה
תקנתא קתני. hach d'leis lei takanta katni. Something that would have no
way to fix it if you שחטed shecht the animal before daybreak,
you got a dead animal, so that we had to make sure
that we're very careful that you waited for the announcement before שחיטהing
shecht the animal. הך דאית ליה תקנתא, hach d'is lei takanta, something
that if you got it wrong, fine, take the logs of wood
off and put it back on, לא קתני, lo katni, so they
didn't necessarily wait for the announcement. Meaning, as רש״י Rashi says, they
pretty much knew when it was daybreak. There was one time when
they made a mistake, so to cover them for that one time
that they made a mistake, they always now had a new announcement.
But pretty much they knew anyway, so they didn't wait for the
announcement for the logs of wood, that they could always correct. They
waited for the announcement for the שחיטה shechita of the תמיד. So
what have we concluded? Besides the fact of the הפסק hefsek between
the two of them based on the פסוקים, we've learned that pretty
much everything else requires a כהן. But now we had this bizarre
thing that even though the פסוקים say the סידור המערכה sidur hama'aracha
and שני גזירי עצים require a כהן, we have now said because
they're night עבודה, avodah, כשרה בזר. kesheira b'zar. And what we have
therefore said is that if there's a חיוב, chiyuv, it's on the
wood, and that's because the wood actually would take place in the
day, not at the night.
Okay.